Guide to the New-York Historical Society Bequests, Gifts & Related Matters Record Group 1852-1992 NYHS-RG 16
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Bequests to Circa 1960, 1852-1986; 5.42 Linear feet in 13 document boxes
  - Hudson River Chain Links, 1880, 1924, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes an account in multiple forms (handwritten and typescript) of the Revolutionary War era chain. Also includes a clipping of a letter to the editor (1880) written by J.C. Pumpelly of the Society of the Sons of the American Revolution; also from Pumpelly in the file is a piece of wood annotated to indicate it is from Old Arnold's Tavern in Morristown, NJ.
  - Hungerford, Edward, 1947, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Loan of models of steamboats.
  - Jaffray, Lydia Butler, 1950-1951, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Bequest of family portraits.
  - Johnston, Elvey Kate, 1933, 1935-1936, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Bequest of a medical case.
  - Jones, Frank C., 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Bequest of sword, scabbard, urn, and certificate associated with Captain Jacob Jones (1768-1850).
  - Jones, John Divine (3 folders), 1874-circa 1884 (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
    Financial gifts establishing the John Divine Jones Fund to produce print volumes. The files include the original documents concerning the donation and the financial records for production of the first volume paid by the Fund, Thomas Jones's History of New York During the Revolutionary War.
  - Jones, Julia C. Van Arsdale, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Essex County, NJ, Orphans Court notices only.
  - Juhring, John C., 1930-1947 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Karstens, Carrie E., 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Kaufman, Enit, 1946-1948, 1955, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Donation of the artist's collection of portraits "The American Century" (1946-47), despite an objection on the Art Committee. Includes a letter objecting to the appearance of a partisan political bias in the exhibition of the work (1948). Includes Kaufman's husband's request for an exhibition of the works shortly after the artist's death (1961).
  - Keep, Austin Baxter, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Bequest of lantern slides, negatives, prints, and other material related to the history of libraries in the American colonies.
  - Keteltas, Henry, 1861, 1894, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - King, Ellen, 1921, 1928-1931, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - King, Mary Rhinelander, 1909-1910 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - King, Nancy W., 1904-1905 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Bequest of the Rufus King Library, to be purchased by the estate and donated to N-YHS.
  - King, Rufus, 1953, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Bequest of portrait painting of Edward King by John Trumbull.
  - Knight, Elizabeth B., 1940 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Kreischer, Louise, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Bequest of engravings, miniatures, daguerreotype, and other objects.
  - Lafayette Camp No. 140, Sons of Union Veterans of the Civil War, Department of New York, 1915, 1923, 1930-1931, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Gift of a vase presented to Lafayette Post No. 140 by Bartholdi in 1887 (1923). Loan (1930) and return (1968) of a chair purportedly used by Lafayette during the Revolutionary War. Gift of a flag presented to Camp No. 140 by William Tecumseh Sherman in 1889 (1931).
  - Lafayette Punch Bowl, 1910, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Gift of bowl from Rosalie Mercein Heiser and John Jay Heiser.
  - Lawrence, Townsend, 1951-1952, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Bequest of furniture.
  - Leavitt, Sheldon, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Bequest of furniture, silverware, and vases.
  - Lefferts, Charles M., 1923 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Acquisition of books, photographs, paintings, and other items from the beneficiaries of Lefferts's estate.
  - LeRoy, Stuyvesant, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Bequest of a portrait.
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Portrait), 1926 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Includes only a print advertisement from Oscar Marshall concerning the engraved portraits of Lincoln and General Grant by William E. Marshall, and a typescript copy of an 1887 letter complimenting the artist on the Lincoln piece.
  - Livingston, Robert R. Collection (4 folders), 1945-1947, 1950-1954, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
    Gifts of books, manuscripts, paintings, and many other objects from various members of the Livingston family.
  - Lockman, DeWitt M., 1933, 1956-1959, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Purchase of 12 portrait paintings from the artist (1933). Bequest of portraits. Renunciation of bequest of certain drawings and paintings, and related financial legacy.
  - Loubat, Joseph Florimond, 1918, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Bequest of patents of nobility, citizenship, etc.
  - Ludlow, James B., 1921, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Return of a silver-oar, held on loan, to the estate beneficiary.
  - Luther, Martin. Ring, 1915, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Betrothal ring of Martin Luther placed on deposit at N-YHS and later returned to the estate of Hildegard Pinkert.
  - MacDonald, Pirie, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Gift from the photographer's daughter, Patricia MacDonald Tutchings, of 493 photographic prints to be known as the "Pirie MacDonald Collection of Portraits of Men," with loan of supplementary materials for possible exhibition use.
  - Mackie, Catherine R.B., 1947-1950 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Renunciation of bequest of furniture.
  - Marié, Peter, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Gift from legatees of Marié's estate of about 275 miniatures to be known as the "Peter Marié Collection of Miniatures." Includes list of eight miniatures attributed to Clausen Coope (J.C. Coope).
  - Marine Museum of the City of New York (2 folders), 1938-1939, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    Consideration in 1938 and again in 1952 of the Marine Museum donating its collection to N-YHS. Includes a catalogue of the Marine Museum's collection at 1952.
  - Marquand, Fanny E., 1949, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Bequest of bust carved from wood.
  - Marwick, Sarah Brewster, 1942, 1945-1946 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Bequest of three Macy portraits.
  - Masten, Arthur H., 1934, 1936-37 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mather, Frederic G., 1924 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Deposit, and gift under certain conditions, of materials related to the War of 1812.
  - McLean, Henry C., 1954, 1956, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Bequest of legatee's journals of his military service.
  - McWhorter, George C., 1895 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Inventory of items from McWhorter.
  - Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the U.S., Commandery of the State of New York, 1926, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Donation of Commandery's library of Civil War books, including an original impression of the terms of surrender at Appomattox, and photographs (1926).
  - Mitchell, Albert M.P., 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Moberly, Edna Maude, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Bequest of theater programs and autographs.
  - Moore, Thomas W.C., 1858 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Bequest of letters of Washington, Hancock, Zachary Taylor, and others, and several paintings.
  - Morris, Jr., John B., 1957, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Bequest of silver and other objects.
  - Munn, Charles Allen, 1924, 1935, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Bequest of statues, statuettes, medallions, etc. (1924). Deposit by (1924, 1935), and return to (1943), Mrs. I. Sheldon Tilney manuscripts, maps, books, and other matter known as the Charles Allen Munn Collection.
  - Munn, Margaret Crosby, 1942, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Bequest of two paintings by George Frederick Munn.
  - Murdock Collection, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Purchase from Mrs. George Murdock, Jr. of her late father-in-law's collection of notes and other documentation related to steamboats.
  - Murphy, Katharine Prentis, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Gift of four oil portraits and a silver cup (including accession numbers 1951.1 to 1951.4). Financial gift. Includes correspondence related to the acquisition of the Prentis Murphy collection and preparations of the period rooms for their display. See also folders below for Prentis, Edmund Astley and for Prentis-Murphy Collection.
  - Nadelman Folk Art Collection, 1937-1942 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Purchase of Elie Nadelman's collection. Includes some correspondence concerning the preparations for the display of the collection at N-YHS.
  - Nash Collection, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Purchase by Samuel V. Hoffman for N-YHS from George W. Nash of Nash's collection of household objects and church models from Hurley, New York.
  - Naval and Military Order of the Spanish-American War, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 23a)
    Permanent deposit of the Order's records.
  - Naval History Society, 1924-1926, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 23b)
    Includes documents related to Franklin D. Roosevelt's proposed amalgamation of the Ship Model Society, Marine Society, and Naval History Society with N-YHS (1924); includes a document that is likely Roosevelt's proposal, Alexander J. Wall's notes of a Ship Model Society meeting at which the proposal was discussed, and a report of a visit to Roosevelt by N-YHS representatives. Also includes documents related to the donation of the Naval History Society's collection and to N-YHS and the establishment of the Naval History Fund (1925-26). Documents from 1977 relate to the publishing of select materials from the collection.
  - Newcomb, Estella, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Deposition concerning provenance and owership of a butler bowl.
  - Newton, Lulu, 1959, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Bequest of a needlepoint sampler marked "Emily Almire Chappell 1830."
  - New York Law Institute, 1945-1946 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Long term loan from the Institute's library of a portrait of Thomas Addis Emmit.
  - Nineveh Sculptures, 1858-1859 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Donation by James Lenox of 13 Assyrian marble reliefs he purchased for N-YHS from Henry Stevens. Includes correspondence related to the shipment of the reliefs to N-YHS from Boston and other locations.
  - Noyes, Pauline Riggs, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Bequest of three portraits of Mr. and Mrs. Wynant Van Zandt.
  - Ogden, Henry A., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Notes about Henry Ogden and the collection of drawings, manuscript notes, lantern slides, and other items received from Ogden's estate.
  - Orvis, Edwin W., 1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Gift of 82 paperweights. Financial legacy.
  - Pach Brothers, 1937-1938, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Purchase by Philip M. Plant of the Pach Brothers's photographs displayed in their exhibition "American Personalities Through Seven Decades" and donated through Pach to N-YHS (1938). Loan of photographs by N-YHS to Pach for exhibition with indication that additional photographs would be donated by Pach to the collection (1946).
  - Paltsis, Victor Hugo, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Financial legacy. Purchase from estate of a set of Stokes Iconography of Manhattan Island. Gift from Paltsis's children of various papers.
  - Parish, Jr., Daniel, 1912, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Bequest of books, pamphlets, etc.
  - Parkes, Grace E., 1957 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Bequest of three portrait paintings of the Maverick family.
  - Pell, Cornelia L., 1938-1939, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Bequest of two Livingston portraits and a financial legacy.
  - Pell, Howland, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Financial gift to establish the "Howland Gallatin Pell Binding Fund."
  - Pennington, Roberta K., 1933, 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Bequest of a coffee cup formerly owned by President Monroe.
  - Phoenix, Stephen Whitney, 1881, 1883 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Bequest of books and manuscripts and a financial legacy. The folder includes a printed copy of Phoenix's will, memorials, and photocopies of accession cards recording Phoenix's donations and bequest.
  - Pool, Eugene H., 1942-1943, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Gift of manuscripts and other items concerning Captain James Lawrence (1942). One item, considered to be a loan, returned to Pool's son (1949).
  - Post, George B., 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Deposit by Edward Everett Post of correspondence, drawings and material related to the practice of his grandfather, George B. Post, and the firm of Geo. B. Post & Sons.
  - Powell, Elsie K. (Mrs. William M.), 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Correspondence concerning the Knapp family collection.
  - Prentis, Edmund Astley, 1950-1952 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Gift, with Katherine Prentis Murphy, of colonial furniture and its installation in rooms at N-YHS. Gifts of paintings, court cupboard, spoons, and other objects. Financial contributions. Conveyance of gift from Mrs. Blake Donaldson of an 1864 publication. Includes a roughly drawn organization chart of N-YHS done by director Vail for Prentis at his request as a new trustee. See also folders above for Murphy, Katharine Prentis and below for Prentis-Murphy Collection.
  - Prentis-Murphy Collection (4 folders), 1949-1982 (Box 8, Folder 14-17)
    Inventories of gifts and loans and summaries of expenses related to the collection (1950-53). Correspondence concerning acquisition (1949-50). Magazine articles. Correspondence concerning the collection (1951-53). Copies of the final wills of Katharine Prentis Murphy and Edmund Astley Prentis (1964-67). Some correspondence concerning the decision to dismantle the Prentis exhibition rooms, thereby relinquishing the collection to Columbia University (1981-82). See also folders above for Prentis, Edmund Astley and for Prentis-Murphy Collection.
  - Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States, 1928-1932, 1947, 1960-1962, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Deposit (1929) and return (1962) of the church archives.
  - Randel, Jr., John, 1871, 1875, 1913, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Deposit of Randel's 19th century maps and field books by Joseph O.B. Webster (1913) and correspondence concerning a possible claim on them (1964). Includes insurance policies (1871) and notice of sale (1875) for the maps.
  - Redmond, Julie Parsons, 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Bequest of two lithographs.
  - Reford, Robert W., 1949 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    Purchase receipt for watercolor A Surround by A.J Miller.
  - Roach, John, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Gift from Roach's heirs of silver service set presented to Roach by the Merchants of New York.
  - Rockhill, Blanche Austin, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    Bequest of a Clement C. Moore desk and a map of the Lansing farm.
  - Rogers, Franklin A., 1957, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Bequest of a miniature and a daguerreotype related to the Delancey family.
  - Rogers, Katherine R. (2 folders), 1931-1937, 1948, 1951-1957, 1961, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 25-26)
    Purchase of 35 bronze models of groups sculpted by John Rogers (1936). Gift of a bust of Rogers's son and various letters and other papers (1951). Loan from Mrs. Alexander Parker Rogers of a statuette of Judge Henry E. Howland (1952). Gifts and loans of portraits (1955, 1961). Return of loans (1968, 1973).
  - Sackett, Henry, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    Scope and Contents
    Notice of probate only
  - Saint Nicholas Society, 1923, 1933-39, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    Loan (1923) and return (1934) of weather cock. Loan of weather cock and other objects (1939). Photocopy of accession card indicating return of cock in 1967.
  - Schell, Francis, 1928-1932, 1942, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Schell, Robert, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Schermerhorn, E. Gibert, 1949-1950 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Bequest of a corner cabinet, music stand, candelabra, a medal from the St. Nicholas Society.
  - Schermerhorn, Harriett Pullman, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Schuyler, Louisa Lee, et al., 1907-1927 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Bequest from Harriet L. Schuyler of family portraits bequeathed to N-YHS via Harriet from Philip Schuyler (1915). Financial contributions and bequest of additional portraits from the Schuyler sisters Louisa Lee and Georgina (1916-25), with the involvement of Mary Schuyler Hamilton. Gift of miniature watercolor portrait of Pierre Toussaint, signed Menucci, two others of Toussaint's family members, and one of Madame Jean Berard de Pithou, and other items/documents from Georgina (1920). Gift from Louisa Lee of Sheffield plated ware and glass belonging to General Philip Schuyler (1922). (Georgina died in 1923, Louisa Lee died in 1926.)
  - Scofield, Sarah E., 1909, 1911 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Bequest of silver tea service and other silver objects formerly belonging to Lord Stirling and to Clarkson Crolius.
  - Seventh Regiment Library, 1947-1948 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Gift from the 107th Infantry, New York National Guard, of library, including manuscripts, books and bookcases, portraits, photographs, weapons, and other objects.
  - Servoss, George Hancock, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Shepard, Gerald F., 1937 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Unidentified bequest.
  - Sherrill, George Gibbs, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Revoked bequest of scrapbooks.
  - Shircliffe, Arnold A., 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Gift from Harold A. Shircliffe of his father's collection of more than 10,000 menus, with filing cabinets.
  - Sinclair, Louise A. Spies (Mrs. Charles D.), 1929 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Bequest of three silver objects and a financial legacy.
  - Sloane, William, 1922, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Smedberg, Bessie Clarkson, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Bequest of bound volumes of Kith and Kin.
  - Smith, Herbert L., 1953, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Bequest of Smith and Farrington genealogies.
  - Smith, James Reuel (5 folders), 1905, 1918, 1935-1939 (Box 9, Folder 14-18)
    Bequest of manuscripts, photographs, and other material, and financial legacy for purpose of publishing Smith's writings. Includes biographical and other research and production notes related to the preparation at N-YHS of the resulting publication Springs and Wells of Manhattan and the Bronx. Includes correspondence related to the distribution of the publication to Smith family members and others.
  - Sons of Rhode Island in New York, 1866 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Deposit from the organization upon its dissolution of its records, banner, and other items. Creation of the Fund of the Sons of Rhode Island in New York for purchasing materials concerning Rhode Island history.
  - Spofford, Adelaide T., 1951 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Bequest of silver tray with engraving of the Red Brick Presbyterian Church of New York.
  - Staats, Richard H., 1955 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Bequest of the family's Dutch Bible.
  - Stevens, Eliza L.W., 1928 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Bequest of engravings, prints, and books, including those from the library of her late husband, Byam K. Stevens.
  - Stillwell, John E., 1940 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Financial beneficiary through Lauretta S. Miller Trust.
  - Stokes, Isaac Newton Phelps, 1868, 1873, 1945-1948 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    Bequest of maps, engravings, photographs, and other items (1945). Gift from estate of a scrapbook concerning the 1908-09 preservation of Trinity Church's St. Paul's Chapel (1945). Gift from estate of painting The Sowing of the Seed by Huntington (1948); includes provenance documentation between Stokes and Huntington (1868, 1873).
  - Stuyvesant, Jr., Augustus Van Horne, 1953-1958 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    Bequest of family tree, a miniature, and a painting (1953). Gift from St. Luke's Hospital of papers, maps, and account book from the estate that were bequeathed to it (1954). Includes correspondence related to objections raised in court by the executors, with N-YHS's urging, over Stuyvesant's will directing the destruction of certain portraits and other objects; items held on deposit at N-YHS during court process. Gift of objects to N-YHS from the estate following the court decision to not follow will's direction (1956-57).
  - Thomas Hunter Association, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    Financial gift.
  - Thompson Family. General (6 folders), 1914-1942 (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
    This folder and the next several labeled "Thompson Family" concern the estates of the siblings Charles, Elizabeth, and Mary Thompson, which eventually resulted in N-YHS, as residuary legatee, receiving a financial bequest.
  - Thompson Family. Charles G. Thompson (3 folders), 1919-1942 (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
  - Thompson Family. Charles G. Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 1), December 1937 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Thompson Family. Charles G. Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 2), December 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Thompson Family. Elizabeth Thompson (2 folders), 1914-35 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Thompson Family. Elizabeth Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 1), December 1937 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Thompson Family. Elizabeth Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 2), December 1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. (1 of 7 folders), 1935-1936 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. (6 of 7 folders), 1935-1943 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. Thompson. Examination of Subscribing Witnesses, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. Thompson. Statements of Witnesses, [1935-1936?] (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 1), 1938 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Thompson Family. Mary G. Thompson. Receipt, Release and Account (Copy 2), 1938 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Thorne, Grace D., 1921 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Tompkins, Hamilton B., 1917, 1922-1924 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Van Cortlandt, Anne S., 1939 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Bequest of silver christening bowl.
  - Van Slyck, George W., 1890, 1922, 1946-1949 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Financial legacy. Includes deed to a burial plot from the reformed Protestant Dutch Church of Kinderhook, NY.
  - Warner, Kate, 1907, 1914-1915 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Bequest of silver, four paintings, and books, and a financial legacy.
  - Warner, Mary E., 1947 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Bequest of a dress worn at Washington's inaugural ball, silver, jewelry, and other items.
  - Washington Arch, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Gift from William R. Stewart of various objects relating to the erection of the Arch at Washington Square. Also, gift from Lispenard Stewart of various framed photographs.
  - Webb, F. Egerton, 1939, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Bequest of the Company flag of the 3rd Connecticut Regiment.
  - Webb, G. Creighton, 1939, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    Gift of objects to N-YHS with intent to bequeath others.
  - Webb, Lena Cadwalader Evans, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    Bequest of books.
  - Weed, Marguerite Hazard Johnson, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Bequest of a miniature by Dodge of John Barent Johnson, silver snuff box, papers, and other items.
  - Weed, Raphael, 1929-1933, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    Bequest of chair used by Edwin Booth, silver wine labels, and a financial legacy.
  - Welch, Fannie Fredericka Dyckman, 1951, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Bequest of oil portraits.
  - Westervelt, Leonidas, 1945-1948, 1955-1956 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    Purchase of Westervelt's Jenny Lind Collection (1945). Gift from H. Alberta Westervelt of her late husband's circus collection (1956). Includes a 1955 inventory of the circus collection.
  - Whitaker, John E., 1921, 1930-1931 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Whitfield, Virginia M., 1956 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Wilbour, Victor, 1933, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    Loan to N-YHS by Cooper Union Museum for the Arts of Decoration of paintings by Wilbourn; a notation indicates these were subsequently donated as a gift to N-YHS.
  - Wilbur, James B., 1929-1933 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    Financial legacy. Includes a list of all gifts made by Wilbur to N-YHS during his lifetime.
  - Wilkin, Florence H., 1911 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    Bequest of books, pamphlets, portraits, and other items.
  - Williams, Horatio B., 1955-1956, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    Bequest of a portrait painting by Carl Wuermer, a silver tea set, and a gold watch made by Robert Roskell.
  - Woodman, Nora D., 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 23)